30 to 70 pull requests in just three months.
That's a big jump and a lot for developers to be in control of, let's say.
Initially, it looked like we were seeing a sublinear increase in outages
correlated with it. Right?
Like our change failure rate appeared initially to be going down.
And then it turned out over the long term
and averaged out so that, you know, we were shipping twice as many pull requests.
And we are seeing, you know, 1.5 times as many incidents.
And there is a limit to how many incidents you can ask a human to work.
Right.
Like your human code review attention is limited.
How do we enable our developers to scale up
not just their ability to produce code, but also their ability to review code?
The AI
Native Dev is a podcast for developers and engineering leads
at the cutting edge of AI and agentic coding.
Join your hosts, Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple,
every week as we chat with the most exciting voices in AI
and tackle the biggest questions facing developers today.
This is the AI Native Dev.
Yesterday you were writing code.
Today you're prompting agents.
Tomorrow you'll be running a software factory.
Agentic coding is moving fast enough to give anyone whiplash.
This June, AI DevCon London sold out. Hundreds of developers,
engineering leads and VP's packed in to hear speakers
from Anthropic, OpenAI, Netlify, and GitHub,
cut through the hype and get to what actually works.
This November, we're bringing it back to New York.
Bigger, bolder, and full of people actually building the agentic future.
Three days of real talks, real tools, real answers.
Whether you're directing the agents, building the loops themselves,
leading the teams, or setting the strategy.
Our early bird pricing ends on September 30th, so make sure you lock in your place before prices increase.
As a podcast listener, you can get 15% off your ticket using promo code POD15.
We have so much planned and we can't wait to have you
join us in New York.
Hello and
welcome to another episode of the AI Native Dev.
My name is Simon Maple. I'm the host for this episode.
And joining me is Liz Fong-Jones, Technical Fellow at Honeycomb.
A massive welcome to Liz.
Hey, how are you going?
How are you doing? Very well, thank you.
And I think this is your first time on the AI Native Dev.
Now, Liz.
You're a technical fellow at Honeycomb, but you actually started
more on the SRE side and then moved into DevRel,
a little bit into field CTO and now a technical fellow.
Tell us a little bit about the journey that you that you've been on.
Yeah, I think over the course of my career,
I focused on being a generalist in the field of reliability,
and I focused on up-leveling the teams that I work with.
So I started as an individual contributor, as all junior devs do.
And then I moved to kind of advising Google SRE teams
and SWE teams on what the best way was to implement reliability practices.
And then I took a swing at the engineer manager pendulum and managed
the Bigtable team at Google, about 12 people under me for a couple of years.
And then I realized that, you know, I could have all the impact in the world
working on one specific team, working with one specific set of people.
But I really wanted to have a broader impact
on the industry, because I could see so many people
that were struggling to implement SRE practices across their organizations.
And I thought, you know, there's a real role
to up-level the industry and to help people get more satisfaction
and not just have ops be this drudge thing, you know?
So that's really what led me down this path of DevRel and field
CTO work is kind of thinking about
how do we move the industry forward and what's the best lever to do that.
And sometimes the best lever to do that is not,
you know, managing one engineering team.
It's funny actually, because
when I also moved from developer relations into the field, CTO really enjoyed it.
Actually, it was at Snyk.
I probably talked more with CISOs and CTOs,
and I kind of felt like it's a little bit like a DevRel kind of role,
but it's just more leveled up into the into the, into the leadership space.
So you're doing leadership coaching, right?
Like, you're working peer to peer
with other executives who are struggling to implement changes across their org.
And that's actually where our similarity ends,
because I moved back into DevRel, because I kind of missed the developers
a little bit more.
But tell us a little bit about the the technical fellow.
Yeah.
So as a technical fellow, I get to do kind of distinguished
engineering work across all of our various engineering teams,
as well as still continuing to hold on to some of that work, to
evangelize and teach and to write about what we're doing.
Really, honestly, the kind of writing and appearing on podcasts
and kind of being able to be that public face of Honeycomb engineering
so that our engineers can primarily focus on being heads down,
except for like, of course, nurture the ones who want to speak publicly.
But. Right, like kind of being that ambassador for what are we doing?
What are we seeing is really, really helpful, especially given Honeycomb's
brand is that we are for forward-thinking engineering teams. Right.
So kind of helping pilot, what does that look like?
And being in a position to give people advice
where we've already seen what the path looks like.
And I'm very openly kind of talked about how this kind of a role,
it really helps technical engineers and technical folks,
you know, progress their careers without needing to drop into that
slippery, that slippery slope, a horrible slope of this management thing.
I remember, I remember my, my, my dad, who was an engineer, actually, engineer
kind of was promoted into a managerial role many, many, many years ago.
And that felt like his promotion.
He succeeded because he went into a managerial role.
But of course, that's not actually
what most engineers are particularly good at or actually want to do.
So I think this is a really strong way of of of leveling folks up without.
I agree.
And also I think it does make engineers better engineers
to take a turn at management at least once in their careers,
even if they don't decide to do it full time longer term.
I think it gives you a level of visibility into how engineering organizations
work, how to have impact as a senior engineer.
So I wouldn't say necessarily that, you know, I agree with your premise
that being a manager is not the promotion, but also I would say that it shouldn't
be something where engineers should,
you know, steer away from it and say, oh God, no, I'm never going to do that.
Right.
Because I think you have a lot to learn from doing it at least once. Yes.
Oh, that's so true. That was my experience.
I totally agree that actually, I think I think the, the and I think today
more than ever, you know, the personal skills,
or, you know, interaction, the communication with AI as well as other
people is so important to be able to, to, to vocalize, to vocalize those things.
Now, one of the things I love doing, Liz,
on, on this podcast is finding quotes from people
and and throwing it back at them and saying, let's chat about this.
Let's see if this still holds up.
Now, one of the things that I actually
completely agree with here, actually, so it's your line
was AI amplifies your existing practices.
It makes a dysfunctional org more dysfunctional
and a high ownership org faster.
Now let's I totally agree with that.
But let's define what is a dysfunctional org.
What are the traits or the things that you would see and say, yes,
if you add AI there, it'll actually make you get to that bad state faster.
What would you see as those flags?
Oh man,
I actually prefer to talk
about the inverse of that and talk about the traits of the functional orgs,
rather than talk about the traits of the dysfunctional orgs,
because I think there's just so many different varieties
of dysfunction out there that it's hard to enumerate them all.
But I think, you know, let's anchor on what you said about ownership, though.
I think ownership is really
that primary force that dictates whether an org is high or low functioning.
And it's the extent to which developers view their contributions
as something that they take a sense of pride in, that they want to own
the life cycle of end to end, that they are responsible for,
and that they are happy to sign their name to.
And I think everything else
kind of flows out of that, because when we talk about reliability practices,
an organization that has poor reliability practices likely does not have
a strong sense of ownership, because otherwise, why would you let
broken code ship to production and leave it broken in prod, right.
So we can talk about all the ways that you can leave broken code in prod.
But I think it fundamentally boils down to
are the developers allowed to follow it into production?
Can they do so right,
like without having to go and ask for five sets of permissions?
And are they actually following through.
Right.
So you know we here I think this was in the news recently.
Tobi Lütke, the CEO of Shopify,
said, you know, 12 months ago, we are now an AI first org.
Everyone should be using AI.
And then literally a week ago, he lamented slop bombs
being lobbed by engineers at production and at their teams.
I'm like, man, that was kind of a foreseeable consequence.
If you were telling people to move without ownership and just, you know, use
AI and move faster and you know, who cares about the consequences,
and now suddenly they're reaping the consequences, right?
So I think, you know, ownership of not lobbing
slop bombs because you are responsible and accountable for what you ship.
Right? Like, I think I think that's that's the important thing.
So, so and.
You say that the bearing here is more important
than the speed in terms of if you're you will,
you will actually accelerate to the destination faster.
And if you're doing something bad and I think the, the.
If and if you are not steering any particular direction, right, like,
you know, you add rocket, you know, rocket fuel to a rocket
that has no steering or guidance and just go in circles until it blows up.
Right?
Yeah, I think that's the classic example of, you know, of of acceleration
without direction yields just going in circles. Yes.
And I guess,
you know, my
takeaway there is AI is not going to fix any existing problems that you have.
It's going to magnify them.
So if you have a problem, AI won't fix it.
You need to fix the problem
and then introduce AI to to accelerate the the path that you're on.
Right.
If you're not in alignment about what you should be shipping,
then you're just going to ship more random acts of engineering, right?
Like that's not good for anyone.
Certainly, I know that customers have a very
limited patience for the amount that they allow their UI to change, right?
If the Riverside podcast recording software
looked different every time I log, every time I logged in, every single week,
I'd become very frustrated very quickly. Right?
Like, there are limits to how much you can introduce,
and you have to think consciously about how you're spending that churn.
So I really like the example
that you gave about ownership there, because I think
and I think there's almost like that willingness for employees, for developers
to say, actually, yeah, I want to see this through to production.
Beyond ownership, are there other,
other traits of a repo where you would look at something and say, oh, actually,
yeah, these people are using these folks that the developers are using autonomy.
Well, or,
you know, strong patterns.
And it's actually very easy to add AI in.
Maybe it's DevOps practices.
Are there other things that you can look at a repo and say this is AI ready?
Yeah.
So I think one primary thing is AI copies existing patterns
that exist in your code base.
If you have five different ways of doing something, it will become very confused
and it will create six ways or seven ways of doing it.
So I think making sure that you have alignment in your engineering
organization about how do you do things, what are the common patterns, as you say,
and then making sure to encode for AI and also for your new hires?
Where do you find these patterns? How do you use them?
And I think, you know, taking your nudge there, right.
Like it is important as well to have strong CI/CD patterns
so that you can actually validate things with five minutes of effort
and not 60 minutes or 3 hours of effort, making sure that you have good
observability, making sure you have good testability, and not just,
you know, empty calorie tests, but actual like real, meaningful tests, right?
Again, machines copy, and if they are copying bad practices,
then you're going to wind up creating smartphones.
If you are copying good practices, then you are going to have an easier
time testing and validating what you're producing.
And that starts with testing, starts with high quality comments.
And even in our code base, where we have relatively high quality
comments, we found that AI unfortunately is regressing us to the mean there.
We're having like lots of very low, low-value comments that AI is creating, right?
Like, so how are you guarding against AI making your code base worse?
How are you actually propagating good patterns around testing,
good patterns around observability, kind of making sure that we are
engineering things
in a way that it's going to be easier to roll them out to production.
And I think we talked about this briefly off air,
but the advice that we kind of like giving here
is actually the same advice that we would give pre
AI in terms of what functional looks like, what good looks like,
you know, good testing, good reliability, all of those things.
This is just.
Good old telling people to eat their
vegetables, right.
And and the trouble is no one wants to eat their vegetables.
Until they wind up with a vitamin deficiency. Right?
Like, yeah, except for the thing is.
AI has made it a lot easier to do the eat your vegetables part.
As long as you tell AI to do it and not just have AI, you know, slop
coding a bunch of new features into your codebase, right?
Like you have a bunch of new engineering bandwidth.
How you choose to spend it is up to you.
And because the machines never get bored,
it's a great thing to do to have them add telemetry to your code base, right?
Like to add rich wide events, to add attributes.
Right.
Like these are things that we used to have to tell developers,
you know, like like telling them to eat their vegetables or brush their teeth.
Right now, it's something that the robots are actually pretty competent at doing,
and they're happy to do it as long as you instruct them to. Right?
Like so. I think it's both. The
necessity of doing it is higher than ever,
because we're having this increased volume of code that we're trying to land,
and also the ease of doing it is much better as well.
Yeah. No. Absolutely.
So let's talk about a functional organization.
Let's talk about Honeycomb.
Let's talk about the Honeycomb bot Autobot.
Sorry.
That merges pull requests and creates pull requests.
I believe that went from 30 pull requests
merged per day to 70 pull requests merged per day in three months.
Is that. Did I get those numbers right?
You have the numbers, right.
But I think the attribution is wrong.
So yes, we do have a internal coding bot called Autobot.
However, the Autobot is producing maybe five of those pull requests per day,
so it's not the majority creator of the pull requests,
it is the 100% reviewer of those pull requests.
And it has gotten so good that our developers are no longer needing
to look for trivial bugs in changes. Right?
So I think, you know, when we're talking about increasing
your number of pull requests by a factor of two or more, right?
Like your human code review, attention is limited.
How do we enable our developers to scale up
not just their ability to produce code, but also their ability to review code?
And I think it really helps there to have
a helpful assistant like Autobot pointing out problems
so that the developer doesn't have to be a human lint or a human bug checker.
Right.
And this is really interesting because the speed at which people
can write code and, and trying to deliver code is not the problem here.
It's the problem is the speed at which us
as humans can validate that the code that is being generated, the pull requests
that are coming in are valid, are correct, are well tested.
And like I would argue, any real production system
should probably not be a dark factory, at least at this time.
I think there is a need for human oversight, human review,
human accountability. As I was talking about.
Right?
Like, you know,
how are we making sure that we're feeding back the lessons that we learn?
How are we making sure that we are maintaining our standards?
And I think those standards have to come from humans.
Right.
Like, I don't I don't think the robots are capable
of coming up with enforcing the standards in their own right.
Like we have to like
just because you have adaptive cruise control in your car
doesn't mean that you can fully let go of the wheel, right?
Like you still have to pay attention.
So can you tell us a little bit how the Autobot, and I love the
I love the name Autobot, but it does sound very Transformers-like.
So it feels like it feels like we've got a lot of power on our side.
Tell us a little bit about how that works under the covers.
Why is it so reliable?
Yeah.
So originally we conceived of Autobot as this mechanism
to automate the creation of small, kind of bite sized pull requests.
And, you know, we developed we invested a fair amount of time
in essentially doing Claude Code in a box to work on a single Linear ticket.
And it still does that, although we're in the process
of sunsetting that, because it turns out that now it's, you know, commoditized,
and now you can have bespoke services that do that in a box for you.
But I think at the time when we started this effort in April or May, this was
phenomenally effective in terms of, for the first time, having even developers
who are not super fluent in Claude Code be able to say, you know what?
This this ticket looks relatively simple.
You know, nothing ventured, nothing gained, right?
Like, you know,
let's assign that ticket to Autobot, see what pull request it produces.
Right.
So that's that's kind of how Autobot started was it was this effort
to kind of clear off the lower hanging fruit that doesn't require
a developer to supervise and tell the robot
consistently and steer it right, like, you know,
this is the kind of design direction I want this to take.
The theory was if you decomposed everything into a Linear ticket
well enough so that it would be able to, you know, complete
the Linear ticket on its own, that then your Autobot could take that
and turn it into a pull request,
and then you could, as a human who requested the Autobot to run,
you could go ahead and and review that self review first,
and then after that hand that to your peer reviewer to to review as well.
So that's how it started.
And then we realized that
there were a relatively small percentage of these smaller tickets.
And also that same functionality could also be used to reproduce
kind of in a box, the functionality that I think in April or March
this year, Anthropic released this Claude Code review functionality
and it's phenomenally expensive.
That's like 20 or $30 per run.
And it took like 10 or 20 minutes to run.
And we looked at it and we said, actually, we want something like this.
But we would prefer that it run within less than 2
or 3 minutes, that it costs dollars per pull request and not tens of dollars.
So we
pivoted the Autobot project towards handling reviews,
because we realized that our human developers were more
than capable of creating this mass volume pull requests anyways, Autobot or not,
and that we needed to focus that instead on
how do we make the review load for human reviewers lighter.
And how does so obviously,
you know, Claude as a, as a, as an LLM
or a general LLM,
these types of things will always be kind of like very expensive
and long to run in the news this week.
So this will tell folks when we recorded it.
Obviously Jev is making a lot of waves right now.
It's hitting the it's hitting the headlines in most places.
With with an M, which is very specific to kind of being able to provide,
you know, yes no answers or multiple choice does that.
How will that now impact places
or, you know, specific tasks like code review.
Yeah.
So I think the primary place where we're thinking about deploying Jev
right now is classifying pull requests into safe to merge
with just the automatic review versus not safe to merge requires a human review.
Previously, we had been relying on humans to self-identify, and we were doing this
experiment actually to try to have about 20% of our pull requests
automatically reviewed and landed without having a human review.
Kind of like, again,
focusing that human attention, because if you double
the number of pull requests, either you double the amount of more than double
the amount of time that you're spending as a human reviewing, or you have to load
shed, you have to figure out
what's less important to review and what's more important to review.
So previously we had been doing this experiment
of having humans and the reviewers labeling, you know, do I think that
this is a pull request that requires high effort to review or not?
And, you know, now I think we can have Jev do that.
Right.
Like we can have Jev be that gut check of can I trust the reviewers opinion
on whether or not this is safe to land, and if so, go ahead and land it
without human intervention. Right.
So there's still is the language model layer doing the code review.
But I think the classifier is then doing that work of
how complex is the code change.
Did the reviewer raise any significant concerns?
Should I should I merge or not?
Yeah.
And I think there are three kind of like key things that are hitting the news here
with with Jev. One is the cost.
One is the speed, but the other is the confidence score.
And I presume it's the,
the speed and the and the cost are probably the nice to have here.
But it's the confidence score I guess. Right. Exactly.
If I'm already.
Spending five minutes and ten and $10 in tokens to review
to review this pull request, the thing that's actually important
here is getting a automated confidence score on can I land this safely?
Right. So yeah, 100% agree. Right.
But for us again, this is not
that we're intending to spend less time doing code reviews than we did before.
It's to focus the time that we're spending
doing code reviews on the design patterns and not on trivial bugs,
and on the more complex PRs, and not on the more simple PRs, right?
If I'm twiddling a single config knob, most of the time, that's not a big deal,
except for some of the time it actually has the potential to bring down
production, right?
Like so I think that's that's kind of that that tradeoff there. Right.
Like and I as a human can of course opt out of automatic code review.
Right. Like entirely right. Like and say, hey, this requires special caution.
But honestly, right.
Like most developers are very conscientious.
Right. Like at least in a high autonomy org.
So we don't want to cause outages in production.
So by definition,
you know, outages happen when something happens
that was unexpected, that we didn't foresee, that we thought
it was going to be a simple change and was not right.
Like, so having these additional guardrails,
whether it be a language model, doing a review or Jev,
doing a sanity check of does this make sense or not to to immediately land.
Right.
Like, I think those are the levers that we need to do to really go beyond
beyond two x.
Because we've hit the...
Like, candidly, we have hit the ceiling of how much code we can conceive of
and review.
And this is interesting because whenever we hit the ceiling,
we always tend to go beyond it when in a way we kind of like least expect.
But, you know, 30 to 70 pull requests in just three months.
That's like a, that's a, that's a big jump.
And a lot for developers to be in control of, let's say.
Yes. And we.
Definitely initially it looked like we were seeing
a sublinear increase in outages correlated with it.
Right.
Like our change failure rate appeared initially to be going down.
And then it turned out over the long term and averaged out so that, you know,
we were shipping twice as many pull requests.
And we are seeing, you know, 1.5 times as many incidents.
And there is a limit to how many incidents you can ask a human to work.
Right. Like so.
Yeah. Right.
Like we we have to start looking at how do we de-risk the other thing,
these other things.
So where's the line, would you say between something that's been reviewed
and something that's been understood because it's almost like,
you know, when I deliver a 500 line pull request versus a, you know, ten line
pull request, one will definitely be scrutinized more than the other.
In the same way, if I was to provide you with 500 pull requests versus one,
there are going to be many more that just, you know, go through with
maybe a, you know, reduced visibility from the human.
How do we how do we make sure that
as humans, we don't just become very blasé
and just push pull requests along and actually understand what happens?
Is this, again, another... maybe it is Jev, the
actual review, the right place to be having that discussion?
Often we find that that is a better place to be talking about it at the project
and at the ticket level than at the pull request level by the time,
especially if generating the code is cheap
and you could do it five times over, right?
Why are we that attached to the way the specific code works
and not to the broader design pattern? Right.
Like that's the thing that we should be aligning on is is the direction correct.
And not, you know, is this implementation exactly correct?
Right.
Like language model can help you understand
what the individual lines of code do. Right.
But the broader pattern, that's something that you
have to hold in your head and that we as humans that are supervising
these systems need to have a consistent picture of
how is this supposed to behave at the macro level?
Yeah.
Let's let's then take it one step further.
Let's say, you know, there's an outage or some, some system fault.
We obviously need to have a look at what we need telemetry data.
And we need observability.
Now you draw quite a hard distinction here
between what telemetry is and what observability is, really, data
versus the ability to truly understand the system.
How does data.
Versus understanding 100% every day?
Well, what is how does.
AI change what understanding a system means?
If a human actually doesn't write that code?
I don't think the human has to write the code.
And also I don't think the human has to do the querying by themselves.
However, examining the outputs of the queries,
that's something that a human has to do
to really kind of internalize and understand how did this outage happen?
What are the other things that we should be looking at that are similar?
How do we prevent this outage from happening again?
Right.
Like so I think having that data,
having it queryable and legible both to the humans
and AI is helpful for them, kind of establishing that feedback loop.
And I don't think it's just at the moment of outage.
I think also in your development cycle, right.
You should be having your language models test the telemetry
that they're producing by querying a dev environment.
Right.
To make sure if I added an attribute, is that attribute present,
do I have the ability to detect if something backlogs.
Right. If something starts queuing. Right.
So I think I think the answer is yes and right.
Like I think yes we have to have telemetry.
Yes, we have to have the ability to analyze that telemetry.
And also it's not just the humans job, and it's not just the robot's job.
It's a joint responsibility to turn the telemetry data into understanding.
Yes. Yeah.
And I guess as someone who has a lot of history
in the world of SRE, you talked a little bit about,
how your opinion on
how people should be using dark factories in production,
how much should we be trusting AI to do with data in an incident?
It would be lovely to think that we can wake up in the morning
and kind of, you know, click a button to say, yes, I can see the
AI agents have identified the problem.
They have done all the the background root cause analysis.
They've suggested the issue.
Sorry, suggested a solution.
They've reviewed it.
I just need to review it myself and push that through.
How how close are we to that today?
And do you see a world.
Depends on how well you are implementing
the practices of the last ten years. Yes.
We have had feature flagging for 10 or 15 years.
Depends on how you know you count Netflix's early stuff, right.
We've had feature flags for 15 for 15 years.
If you were implementing feature flags, well then yes,
a robot with access to MCP can identify which feature flag
will solve your problem and can fix it, can flip the feature flag,
and the telemetry will be recorded both for the robot
who's diagnosing in real time and for you with a cup of coffee
or a Diet Coke in your hand the next morning. Right.
Like if you have that telemetry data recorded
and if you have the controllability, right, like remember
observability and controllability in control theory are duals. Right.
Like if you have both observability and controllability
you do have the ability to not have to wake up at 2 a.m.
because you can actually go ahead and and fix the problem
without necessarily even fully understanding it. Right.
And then to be able to examine what happened after the fact with the kind of,
you know, flight recorder or whatever it is. Right?
So I think.
We're pretty close if and only if you have
working automatic rollbacks, working feature flags,
working observability, if you don't have those things,
your agents are just guessing and throwing darts
at the dartboard and they might cause more chaos than they actually solve.
Yeah.
So it depends very heavily on your production maturity practices.
And it's not so much your trust in the AI.
It's your trust in the system with which the AI environment is running in.
Exactly right.
Our job is to make it so that the tools that the robots have are safe.
Yeah.
If we're having AI exercise, its judgment about whether it's okay
to kill these pods.
I think that that is a very dangerous thing to give your AI agents
the ability to kill random pods in production, right.
We should be giving them tools to abort rollouts, to revert rollouts.
Right? Like so.
I think you have to make sure that the tools are always safe to use
and that the robot's right,
rather than trusting the robots to decide whether or not to call them. Yeah.
Structured, structured functionality that they can that they can use.
And let's talk about let's talk.
And that's really fair.
This is also true about your most junior developer on your team. Yes.
Right.
Like, you know,
if you're making it safe for your junior developer
so they cannot accidentally cause production outages, right.
Like, I think that that's great for your for your robots too.
Hey everyone!
Hope you're enjoying the episode so far.
Our team is working really hard behind the scenes to bring you the best guests,
so we can have the most informative conversations about agentic development,
whether that's talking about the latest
tools, the most efficient workflows, or defining best practices.
But for whatever reason, many of you have yet to subscribe to the channel.
If you're enjoying the podcast and want us to continue to bring you
the very best content,
please do us a favor and hit that subscribe button.
It really does make a difference and lets us continue to improve
the quality of our guests and build an even better product for you.
All right, back to the episode.
Let's talk about let's continue this path down trust and safeguarding.
You you described needing things like CLAUDE.md rules,
MCP-mediated access, least privilege systems,
or all these things which help this safeguarding.
What, in your opinion, have you seen that would be a really
good piece of advice that most teams actually don't think about.
Or, you know, it's great practice like least privilege
is something that we've known for many, many years, decades.
What are the things that teams can do, today
that is just completely non-negotiable to, to, to avoid?
I think the starting point is really hermetic
CI and CD, like to have fast and reproducible CI and CD.
I think that's the foundation of everything.
I think your mention of least privilege is great.
Actually.
I discovered that on on its own actually, Claude has started
when working with Amazon profiles to default to using read-only profiles
if it's provided the option to have both a read-only and read-write profile.
Even if the read-write profile's
technically available, it will still use read-only,
just to be safe, which I think is a great safety practice.
Right?
Like and you can also enforce that right to enforce, you know, hey
commands that use the read-only profile are automatically approved.
Commands that use the read-write profile must use human approval.
Right. Like so I think layers, defense in depth.
I think that those are all really, really great things.
And is there, you know, anything
you think we are over trusting these days in terms of are there
default settings that we should absolutely try and avoid?
I think the main thing that we are
realizing does not scale is having humans click. Yes.
I think that classifiers do a much better job than humans when attention is scarce.
And I think that, you know,
you do have to develop a certain number of repetitions of hitting.
Yes, before you start trusting auto mode.
And you have to have a certain number of repetitions of seeing automatic code
review issues that you wouldn't personally have caught before you start
trusting automatic code review. Right.
But I think eventually you do realize, yes,
I can trust the automated steering, but I'm still going
to keep my eyes on the road, right.
Like but that's very different than, you know, gripping the steering wheel tightly.
Right.
Like so I think, you know, we have a tendency as human beings to micromanage.
We have a tendency to assume that we always do a better job than the robots.
And I think that that is that is the mistake.
Right.
Like, I think I think the mistake is over trusting your ability
to make decisions under time pressure and stress.
And I think that's the situation where a robot that never gets tired
will do a better job than you. Yeah.
And of course, if something does go wrong,
is it the is it the robot's fault or is it the operator's fault?
Now, Honeycomb's AI values state: if your name's on it, you own it.
So tell us a little bit about how far that extends.
I don't think it's about fault.
I think it's about whose responsibility is to clean up
and to think about how do we harden the systems.
This doesn't happen again, right?
You know, if we're talking about,
you know, some kind of failure that leaks into production.
Well, number one,
ideally something going wrong should not bring down all of production.
We should focus on making the failures smaller in blast radius
rather than, rather than trying to prevent them from happening entirely.
And then I think in terms of the accountability.
Right.
Like the main thing is to is to say like, you know, not,
you know, the robot did it.
You know, it's not my fault the robot did it right, like, you know, "Claude did it"
is not a really great excuse for like instead you have to examine, say, okay,
what are my structural biases that caused me to to over trust in this output?
Right.
So actually there's a,
example this, this past week
where I, I was doing some analysis
of a team's that we were rolling out, and I was trying to do the analysis
A/B tested by which shard or which partition ID,
and for some reason, my AI assistant did not find the telemetry field
for partition ID and then it confabulated this thing about how
we need to construct a construct a new telemetry field for partition ID,
I should have rerun the query and actually typed partition.
I need to see whether it automatically dropped down.
I shouldn't have trusted the assistant
when it blithely asserted there was no partition ID field, right?
But then also my accountability.
I told it, okay, if you're missing the partition ID field,
then we need to go and create a pull request to add the partition ID field.
The field was there all along, like, you know, so I wasted some tokens.
I wasted five minutes of a principal engineers time to review the pull request.
That would have added a duplicate partition ID field, right?
Like, you know, where you know, you could you could say, you know,
you know, blame Claude, or you could say, right, like, you know,
I should have been more skeptical about this output.
Like, you know, surely we should have had partition ID,
I should have known that we of course we had partition ID in there.
Like, I should have run the query by myself before I trusted this robot
that said, you know, there's no partition ID field like we need to we,
you know, we need we need one. And I was like, right.
But I signed off on it, right?
Like that's that's my responsibility. Right?
So I think that's that's what we mean.
When we talk about taking ownership,
I think there are more mundane, things beyond beyond code, right.
Like for instance, don't send someone a slop bomb of,
you know, this is, you know, a ten page, ten page Claude artifact, right?
Like, I think that that's, you know, a little bit more, more self-explanatory
of if your name is signed to it, you should you should stand behind it.
And you should ideally have spent as much time reading over
and producing it as the reader is going to take to read it.
But I think the more interesting thing is, as we're talking about here, right?
Like, you know what happens when code that you ship is wrong
for whatever reason, right?
Like, how are we encapsulating the learning
so that Claude doesn't make the mistake over and over and over again, right.
Like it's it's us humans that have to figure out
how do we more effectively use these tools.
And as a practices, let's say,
rather than models get more developed so that we will get to a stage where,
you know, AI can fully build,
test, review and deploy changes,
potentially small, potentially non complex and maybe non-critical systems.
At what stage would a human who hasn't done hasn't been involved in any of that?
What stage would a human own that would, would it not be fair to say if at that
point Claude's name's on it, let's say, or Codex's name's on that, it should own it?
And we essentially say we are happy
that a, a very small percentage of these will be wrong,
but it's the bot that effectively owns that delivery through to production.
Yeah, I think at.
That point it's the human team that creates. The.
Workflow files, that guide, that loop, that are responsible
for the quality control and checking of that loop and the tuning
of it to make sure that it is as effective as it's supposed to be.
Okay, despite what you might be seeing in the news,
there is not actually fully automated recursive self-improvement, right?
Like there is always some degree of human guidance involved.
So even if robots are coming up with tickets
and solving the tickets and pushing them through and debugging them in production,
there is still a person that owns the system prompt for that.
There's still the person who is paying for the quota for that,
there is still the person that expects the results from that.
Right.
And I think that that is where the ownership lies, is to go and spot
check some of those pull requests every now and then to do evals to
to the system prompt.
Right.
Like, I don't think that we are at a point yet
where we can say we're just going to go fully hands off.
Yeah, sure.
If you're down to go fully hands off, hand me your checkbook, please.
I will I will take your checkbook. Right.
Like but as
long as humans are paying for it, humans have the right to inspect the results.
Yeah, I think that's what it boils down to.
Right, like, is there still a process owner?
And that process owner is accountable for the results?
Yeah. No. Nicely said.
It's, it's what are we recording on the 22nd of September today.
So we're kind of giving away a little bit about the behind the scenes here.
But on the 22nd, Hacktoberfest is right around the corner.
Now, of course, in years gone by,
there have always been some problems where you get bad human pull requests
which have been raised and mass created, which have annoyed maintainers.
Now today's problem, and of course, you know,
that was largely fixed by having an opt-in style of fest.
But today, even if you opt in, probably a bigger worry is someone's
just going to come up and provide some AI slop pull request.
Now, one of the things that was kind of partly mentioned
previously is that you were considering eliminating external contributions
to open source projects because of the kind of floods
of pull requests that were very slop oriented.
Have you made a decision
around that or any experiences recently in and around that space?
Yeah. So I do think that.
For security reasons and a variety of reasons
related to code style maintainability, I think that maintainers
definitely should continue accepting bug reports.
Whether maintainers accept pull requests is up to their discretion,
because it turns out with a well-equipped bug report,
you can have your agent write a fix for it in your preferred style, right?
So why should you trust someone else's agent where it might be just as much work
to check the work over as if you had done it yourself.
So I think that's kind of my first thought.
Bug reports are always, always valuable as long as they're well formatted
that say exactly, this is what I expected to happen.
This is what actually happened.
This is where I think the problem might be,
but not necessarily proposing a fix and leaving up to the maintainers discretion.
I think the other thing is not relaxing our standards.
Right.
Like we should not have lower standards for AI created
pull requests than human created pull requests.
And also, I've seen efforts both in the academic space
as well as in the open source
and commercial space, to actually require someone to complete a quiz about the work
that they've submitted before they actually get a chance to submit it.
So if you cannot answer basic questions about the pull requests that you
that you submitted,
you probably shouldn't be submitting it because you have no idea what's going on.
Yeah.
The "I am not a robot" button I suppose for a pull request.
"I am not a robot" button. We're actually right.
Like this is the funny thing. You're using slop to fight slop, right?
Like you can have an agent take the pull request and create
a quiz about it that you must pass before you can have it submitted, right?
Like, and I think like, you know, yes, as you say, you know.
Right.
Like you can triage them with AI, right.
Also a very interesting thing.
So my wife works on Google Chrome security, and one of the things
that they're starting to do is they're starting to require that
in order to get fast tracked for your security exploit bug,
you must provide a working repro, or you must provide
something that provides evidence that you crash a chrome process.
No crasher, no no triage.
Right?
Like because otherwise you would have to deal with all of these slop reports.
But if you have something that genuinely crashes the browser, right,
like that is clearly a sign that you are onto something real.
And we should go and invest resources in debugging it.
Right?
So, so like,
I think that there are heuristics that you can apply to open source contributions.
And you know, right, like Linus Torvalds came out in favor of using AI.
Right.
Like Linus Torvalds said, you know,
I think that AI agents have a valuable role to play.
And literally this past week, I have a dev box.
That's a Arm64 box that has an unconventional hardware configuration.
Let's let us say.
And that dev box has a bug
that prevents it from booting on Linux 6.19 and newer.
And I was able to with with Claude Fable's help actually
figure out what the bug was, figure out what a what a working patch for it was.
And the patch was only six lines, right?
It's really not that complex that patch,
but I was the first one to run into this situation,
and it solved a general problem for like a variety of classes of hardware.
So I submitted it upstream
and it went through the normal Linux vetting processes.
It took over two months to land, but it did eventually land right.
Like I think that's a sign that things are working as intended.
Right. Like that.
A genuine patch that is small enough to review,
that has good enough justifications can land regardless of whether it's by,
you know, by humans or not. Yeah.
If we if we're restricting open source contributions to bugs only, though,
versus, you know, the larger, more directional changes
that we might with, with full features, what does that mean for.
Non maintainers.
Should not be suggesting large directional changes
without discussion with the maintainers first. Right.
Like that is the source of the slop bombs.
Just because you can do something and send someone a 10,000 line pull request
does not mean you should. Talk to humans first and get approval.
And then, you know,
at that point you're proceeding as if you were a trusted maintainer on the inside.
If you've gone and sign off on your plan.
So so the path is issue first
long discussions or if it's obvious, short discussions with the maintainers.
And from that point, you probably have enough credibility just through those,
through that discussion to be able to share a pull request.
Because the maintainers have context on what you're trying to do.
Yeah. Excellent.
Excellent. So so open source has a bright future.
I think that it has some structural problems.
I think there is that question of
who is paying for all of those tokens for automatic review and triage.
Right.
So I think that there is the challenge of when you've got a million
developers out there who are all paying for a heavily subsidized $20 a month
OpenAI or Claude or Gemini subscription, right?
Like, you have to prevent those folks from denial-of-servicing
your open source maintainers.
And for critical projects like the Linux kernel or Kubernetes.
Right.
Like the Linux kernel has a automatic review bot called Sashiko.
And Sashiko is fully paid for by Google, right?
Which is great.
So I think corporate sponsorship helps, but I think that there are smaller
projects that received less commercial love that are really, really struggling.
And, you know, certainly there have been efforts to do outreach to them.
For instance, Anthropic has Project Glasswing, which gave access to Mythos
to a bunch of very security critical projects like curl and OpenSSL.
Right.
Like but I think there's kind of this broader problem of
who pays for these tokens, and how do we make sure
that open source maintainers are resourced and they don't burn out?
Yeah, I think that's.
What we're seeing from it's always been before. I just. Smell it.
It is it is.
With we're tripping over all the same problems.
Right. But at a faster rate is very interesting.
And actually, you know, executives have money to spend on it.
Now that is the difference, right? Like, previously, telling people,
Yes you should implement observability. And they're like budget.
What budget.
Now it's like
you need to implement observability or else your AI effort will fail.
Great. Here's some money.
Let's do you know we're a few minutes left.
It's been it's been a wonderful chat. Really really enjoyed it.
But I want to I want to end always with the easiest question, Liz,
which is let's talk about what's going to happen in the next 50 years.
Well, maybe not.
Maybe not 50, but.
50 years. Right? 50 days. Exactly. Right.
So so maybe, maybe we talk about just 2 or 3 years and let's
talk about a role change, or maybe even a change that needs to happen
in the org around an observability engineer.
Do you feel that will still be a role, a standalone role, or a job title in future?
Or do you think that discipline needs to merge into into another role
that exists today?
We've already seen
that site reliability engineering, security engineering,
observability engineering these all broadly fall on the platform
of of platform engineering, as it were.
Right.
Because they are all cross-functional disciplines
that are required by all of the individual development teams,
and they do have their own specialized skill set.
But broadly speaking, our job is to produce the kind of common
standards and tooling that developers need to do their jobs.
So I think the great merger into platform engineering is already well underway
for like, you know, I mentioned security engineering, accessibility engineering.
Right. Like test engineering, right.
Like all of these disciplines where, you know,
you don't want each developer to have to
think about each of these things and be an expert in each of these things.
But it is to some extent, those developers job to ensure that their code
conforms to our org standards. Right.
So I think that's basically the, the the crux of it is observability.
Engineering is not necessarily going to be
about building out your own observability platform.
There are vendors out there.
Or if you're at a similarly large scale, sure, there might be a observability
tooling team or something, but I think the Outreach to developers
piece,
I think that that is something that broadly gets owned
by all of platform engineering and that platform engineering employees,
people from a variety of different specialties
who all collaborate to bring the expertise to the teams that need them.
Yeah. It's interesting.
And I think, yeah, even back in my days at Snyk, this was a
even pre AI,
it made sense for more and more things to be centralized, particularly around
security best practices providing those services.
And I think it makes sense.
Yeah. Exactly right. It's a perfect mapping. Right.
Like security observability.
Testing. Right.
Like all all reliability.
You don't want each dev to have to be an expert in service level objectives.
You want every dev to have service level objectives though.
Yeah. Amazing.
Liz where can we talked about a lot,
but where can people follow up on some of the things that
that you and Honeycomb have been, have been doing and talking about?
We definitely maintain a very active engineering blog.
So if you go to the Honeycomb blog, you'll find writing by
not just me, but also by my colleagues,
Charity Majors, Christine Yen and all of Honeycomb engineering.
And you can find me on the internet basically everywhere as Liz the Grey.
Wonderful. Liz.
It's been an absolute pleasure to chat and really and really enjoyed going
deep in various topics.
So thank you so, so much for your time
and it's been a pleasure having you on the AI Native Dev.
Thank you. Wonderful.
And I hope all of our listeners out there enjoyed it just as much as I did.
Thanks for tuning in and see you on the next session.
Bye for now.
The AI Native
Dev is brought to you by the package manager for skills
and context.
Your hosts are
Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple.
Our producer is Tom Dowler.
The AI Native Dev is not just a podcast, it's a community.
And we host monthly meetups at the Tessl offices in central London.
Visit tessl.io forward slash community to learn more.
And I hope to see you there.